<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vanitie of the present churches, and vncertainty of their preaching, discovered. Wherein the pretended immediate teaching of the spirit, is denyed, and the all-sufficiency of the Scriptures teaching, is maintained. With, a new and true method of reading thereof, for the peace of the mind, and rule of life.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97109</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W693A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1367_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210498</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869291</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869291</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170664</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97109)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170664)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 254:E1367[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vanitie of the present churches, and vncertainty of their preaching, discovered. Wherein the pretended immediate teaching of the spirit, is denyed, and the all-sufficiency of the Scriptures teaching, is maintained. With, a new and true method of reading thereof, for the peace of the mind, and rule of life.</title>
                  <author>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 51, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Clows, and are to be sold in Cornhill, and Popes-Head-Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to William Walwyn. Cf. McMichael and Taft, The writings of William Walwyn, 308-9.</note>
                  <note>Preliminary imprimatur leaf dated February 23, 1648-49.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "march 12 1648"; the 9 in the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian sects --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170664:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VANITIE Of the preſent CHURCHES, AND Vncertainty of their Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, diſcovered.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN The pretended immediate teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Spirit, is denyed, and the all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency of the Scriptures teaching, is maintained.</p>
            <p>WITH, A new and true Method of reading thereof, for the peace of the mind, and rule of life.</p>
            <bibl>Gal. 6. 15. 16</bibl>
            <q>For in Chriſt Jeſus neither Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion availeth any thing, nor uncircumciſion, but a new Creature. And as many as walk according to this rule, peace be on them, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>London, <hi>Printed</hi> by <hi>J. Clows,</hi> and are to be ſold in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> and <hi>Popes-Head-Alley,</hi> 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:170664:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough I diſſent from ſome things in this Treatiſe, and other things ſeème dark and doubtfull to me, yet there are many plain, clear, and evident Truths, of great uſe to all Chriſtians. Therefore that the Truth may be manifeſt to all, And that all Believers and Churches of the Saints may be of one mind, and may edifie the whole body in love. And in all their Doctrines, and Converſations, hold forth the truth as it is contained in the written word, the perfect rule of the ſpirit to guide us into all Truth, and to make us wiſe unto Salvation, through that (one neceſſary thing) Faith, which is in Chriſt Jeſus: which is by the Goſpel, (the power of God to ſalvation) preached unto us. And that errour may be diſcovered, reproved, and corrected, and if poſſible, that the guilty may be convinced, and reformed.</p>
            <p>Therefore: I ſay to this Epiſtle, and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Treatiſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>February 23. 1648-49.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Imprimatur</hi> THEODORE JENNINGS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:170664:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:170664:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170664:3"/>
            <head>The vanity of the preſent Churches, and uncertainty of their Preaching diſcovered, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S there is nothing more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable amongſt men, then a true correſponden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy between the heart, the tongue, &amp; the hand: ſo no thing is more lovely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Chriſtians, then that the Conſcience, the profeſſion and the practice do univerſally agree; &amp; though ſomthing be allowable unto frailty, yet when the defect or diſcord is continued, and that to the reproach of Chriſtianity in generall, and to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of humane ſociety; then certainly a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe is not only requiſite, but the neglect thereof, a ſinne of an high nature.</p>
            <p>And ſo thoſe, whom this diſcourſe now deemeth worthy of reproofe did ſeeme to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170664:4"/> judge, when they condemned the perſecuting practices, of the new rayſed Presbyters, whoſe poſitions and profeſſions whilſt they were perſecuted by the Biſhops, did clearly hold forth a full and compleat liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in the exerciſe of Religion, and juſtly and truly did the Independants reprove them, as their many bookes, of that Subject, do ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently teſtifie: their reproofes were ſharp, and their replyes driven home; whereby they put the queſtion of the utmoſt liberty of Conſcience, out of all queſtion, accompting nothing more baſe, or miſ-beſeeming a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, then to queſtion, or vex, or reproach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man for his judgment or practice, touch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing matters of Religion, and inciting all men to peace, unity, love, and true friendſhip, though of never ſo many ſeverall opinions, or different wayes in Religion.</p>
            <p>By which their ingenuity, they, (as the Puritan Presbyter had done before them) gained abundance of love and reſpect from all men: their Congregations multiplied, and in concluſion, obtained much countenance from authority: which they no ſooner taſted; but inſtantly, ſome of them began to pride themſelves, and to diſpiſe others; and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170664:4"/> and villiſie all ſuch, as upon tryall and examination of their Churches, their Paſtors<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Sermons, finding all to be but fained imitations, nothing reall or ſubſtantiall, forſooke their ſocieties, and thereupon as the Presbyters had uſed them; ſo deale the Independant with theſe, and all that any wayes adhered unto theſe, rayſing nick-names and bitter invective reproaches againſt them, ſparing neither art nor paines, to make them odious to others, and their lives (if it were poſſible) a burthen to themſelves; and though reaſons have been offered, and conferences deſired, that they might ſee their error, and forbeare to deale thus contrary to their poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, owned, and declared principles: yet have they perſiſted therein, and go on ſtill without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſing, manifeſting a moſt deſtructive and perſecuting diſpoſition, not only towards theſe, but towards many others whom they now (as compleat Judges of other mens Conſciences) judge to be erronious, or heriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and ſeeme to have placed their felicity in the ruine of thoſe whom their own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences cannot deny to have been inſtrumentall in their preſervations, and who have, not thought their lives too precious, to purchaſe them that freedom which now they enjoy.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:170664:5"/>
            <p>And therefore it hath been conceived not only juſt, but of abſolute neceſſity, to publiſh to the judgments of all impartial people, both of the Congregationall way and others: this their hard meaſure and unthankful uſage of a harmleſſe well-meaning people, and withall, to diſcover to all thoſe who are conſcientious, the error of their wayes, and emptineſſe of the things wherein they glory, and to let all thoſe who are wilfull or meere polititians a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, beare their ſhame openly, and ſince they are proofe againſt their Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and can take up, and lay down principles, profeſſions, and practices too, as ſtands moſt with their advantage, and like the Jewes in their worſt eſtate, make no reckoning of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing all that are not of their tribes, it is but equall, that ſuch ſhould bear their mark in their forehead, that all men might be warned from converſing with ſuch deceivers, and if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tartneſſe appear herein, they are the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, it being no more then they deſerve.</p>
            <p>And not only ſo, but we have herein alſo indeavoured to ſupport the weake, and by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhing them upon the ſure foundation of the written word of God, (inclining them to give eare thereunto, as unto the only true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible teacher of ſpirituall things in our
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170664:5"/> times) and by directing them in a brief and plain method, in the reading thereof how to attain to that one neceſſary Doctrine and main deſign intended therein unto man, for his temporall and eternall comfort.</p>
            <p>To which end, that we may neither ſeeme to wrong the one ſort, nor to delude the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and for full ſatisfaction of all that are, or ſhall be concerned herein: we affirm it to be moſt palpably evident, That ye of the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant Congregationall, or of any Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way whatſoever, have not that true eſſentiall mark of a true Church to be found amongſt you, which only can diſtinguiſh the true from the falſe, and without which a true Church cannot be:—A true Church in the Scripture ſence; being ſuch only, as wherein the very word of God is purely and infallibly preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: that's the mark.</p>
            <p>Now though it have been uſuall among you in your prayers, to deſire of God that your auditors may give eare to the word that you preach, not as unto the word of a mortall man, but as unto the word of the ever living God: and this too, with ſuch ſolemn counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, lifted up eyes and earneſtneſſe of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, as if it were the ſin of ſinnes, for men to doubt it: Though this hath been
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170664:6"/> your courſe: do ye not tremble when you conſider it, to think that you ſhould ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently practice ſo groſſe an impoſture, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly to pray unto God, that your eronious, doubtfull uncertain conceptions, (for what other are your Sermons) ſhall be heard and received, as the word of the ever living God; what greater impiety, nay blaſphemy, then to call mans word, Gods word, to counterfeit a Preacher an Evangeliſt, an Ambaſſadour of Chriſts, and to deliver a Word, a Meſſage, a Goſpel, mixt and made up of opinions and conjectures, as if it were the true reall word of the ever living God.</p>
            <p>What is this but even to debaſe, belye, and offer deſpite to the ſpirit of God himſelf, for advancing your own falſe Honour and repute amongſt men.</p>
            <p>Conſider this ſeriouſſy, all ye that are cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated with the charmings of theſe Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that are intangled in their formes of godlineſſe, that are drawn into their imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Churches, that are deluded into an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that they are paſtors, feeders, preachers of the word of God, and be ſo true to God; (whoſe honour lyes at ſtake) to your ſelves whoſe peace and comfort lyes at ſtake, and to your Neighbours, whoſe good name lye
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170664:6"/> at ſtake alſo: as to make a clear examination whether theſe pretended paſtors, &amp; Churches are taught immediately by the ſpirit of God, or not, as they pretend; try them by the word they preach.</p>
            <p>And you ſhall find, however they have prepoſſeſt you to the contrary, that neither they, nor your ſelves, have any underſtanding at all of ſuch divine or heavenly things, as bring peace of Conſcience and joy in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-ghoſt, by any other way or meanes, but only and ſolely by the Scriptures, and that neither they, nor your ſelves, are taught by the ſpirit, as they have long perſwaded you, and whereby chiefly they delude you, into a belief that they are true paſtors, and your Churches, true Churches of Chriſt. For Judge you, had they the ſpirit of God as they pretend? would they need, as they do; when they have reſolved to ſpeak to you from a Text of Scripture, to go ſit in their Studies, three or four dayes together, turning over thoſe authors, that have written thereupon; and beating their own braines, to find out the meaning and true intent thereof; no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, had they the ſpirit of God, it could in an inſtant, in the twinkling of an eye, inform them the meaning of his own writings; they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170664:7"/> would not need to be ſtudying, ſeven, ten, or twenty years, to underſtand the truth of the Goſpel, and when they have done ſo too, be as farre to ſeeke as they were at firſt for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny expreſſe certainty therein; for do but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that when they have for ſome years preacht up a Doctrine, they are many times forſt to preach it down again, as ye well know moſt of them have done, and that in very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall points.</p>
            <p>As for inſtance, are they not one while zealous for the baptizing of Infants, another while for the baptizing of Beleevers only, and then again for no Baptiſme at all, for want of a true Miniſtry? do not the Paſtors differ a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, and contentions ariſe not only between Church and Church, but in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Church within it ſelf? are there not ſome that for many years have preacht up e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection and reprobation, and afterwards have as much preacht it down, and cryed up gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall redemption, and, that man hath free will or a negative voice in his ſalvation, and this in a Church gathered and taught by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as they would make the world believe; and thoſe who by praying and preaching <hi>ex tempore,</hi> would be thought to have yet a more immediate teaching of the ſpirit; how
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170664:7"/> extreamly are they to ſeeke in the ready un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the Scriptures, what weake and indiſgeſted matter iſſueth from them, is too eaſily diſcerned, yea what contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they huddle one in the neck of another, though through confidence in the ſpeaker, and ſuperſtition in the hearer, all paſſeth for currant truth.</p>
            <p>But conſider, can it be of the true ſpirit to produce uncertain Doctrines, if the Trumpet give an uncertain ſound, who can prepare himſelf to the battle; ſo if the preacher, preach uncertainly, how can he affirm his word to be the word of God; or how from ſuch doubtfulneſſe can true faith be begotten in the hearts of the hearers? is not a Church founded upon ſuch uncertainty, founded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſand, and built up with hay &amp; ſtubble, not able to ſtand the leaſt blaſt of a reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble oppoſition; and will ye that have Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences towards God, any longer be inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this mocking of him, and by your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance thereof partake with them in this ſtrong deluſion?</p>
            <p>What doth the Pope and his Clergy more then belye themſelves, and blaſpheam God, in ſaying, they have the true ſpirit of God, which leads them into all truth; whilſt by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170664:8"/> their lying miracles, by their art and ſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, they lead the poor deluded people in the greateſt errors, for maintenance of their own pride, covetouſneſſe, and luxury: The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops they come, and by pretence of the true ſpirit, diſcover abundance of faults in the Pope and his Clergy, and make ſhew of great reformation; but advance only themſelves and their uncertain Doctrines, for their own ambitious ends only, without any regard to the glory of God, or good of men: then comes the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and they cry out againſt <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> (that was faulty enough) and ſtudied Sermons, as ſtinters, and ſuppreſſors of the true Spirit of God in them; and they are no ſooner in the Chaire, and their Prayers &amp; preachings examined; but they alſo are found to differ one with another, to contradict themſelves, &amp; to mind only their own honour and profit; and to be poſſeſſed (as both the former) with a perſecuting Spirit, which is abhorred of God, of Chriſt, and of all his true Miniſters and Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Then comes the <hi>Independents</hi> and pretend to erect, a holy, pure and undefiled wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, according to the pattern, ſhewed unto them by the true Spirit indeed, pleading for generall liberty of conſcience, void of all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170664:8"/> or reſtriction, and profeſſing the meeknes of the very Lambs of Chriſt, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility towards all men; who now could have ſuſpected what ſince hath been diſcovered? Namely, that they as the reſt, belyed the Spirit of God, (pardon the harſhnes of the expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, its for Gods cauſe and muſt be ſpoken) they being no more infallibly certain of the truth, they raiſe from Scriptures<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then any of thoſe whom they ſo much condemn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they as the reſt, pray, preach, and do all for mony, and without it they do nothing, taking mony for that which is not bread, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſand mixt together; that di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eople ſwallow it whole, without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, it would be as gravell between their teeth, and they would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it out of their mouths.</p>
            <p>And ſince, they are increaſed in number<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and have as it were, ſcumm'd the Pariſh Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations of moſt of their wealthy and zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous members. Do they not fully diſcover a ſerpentine diſpoſition hankering after perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution? Do they not dayly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their venom privatly and publickly, againſt any that either ſeperate from them, or joyne not with the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and that in as foul aſpertions, as ever the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> uttered againſt <hi>Luther,</hi> the <hi>Biſhops</hi> againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170664:9"/> 
               <hi>Puritan,</hi> or the <hi>Presbyter</hi> againſt the <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,</hi> are they not high and skillfull in rayling? making whom they pleaſe <hi>Atheiſts, Anti-ſcripturiſts, Autinomians, Anti-magiſtrats, Polligamiſts, Seekers,</hi> or what they will: and can theſe proceed from the true Spirit of God, or from the Spirit of <hi>Antichriſt?</hi> Judge impartially. Yee that are yet untainted in your conſciences (going on in this Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way as deceived, and not deceivers) whether yee can offer more diſpite to the Spirit of Grace, then by your preſence and ſociety, to juſtifie this deluſion; or to uphold this new Idoll, this Apple of <hi>Sodome,</hi> ſeeming onely faire to the eye, but touch it, and it falls to powder, to the very earth, being nought but earth, like <hi>Dagon</hi> before the Arke, having neither hands nor feet, but to (diſcerning eyes) is a meere uſeleſſe lump, an Idoll, which as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>is nothing in the world,</hi> and therefore let none, who minde the things that are of God, uphold it any longer.</p>
            <p>It being hardly to be beleeved, the infinite evils which comes to the world by this falſe ſuppoſition and aſſumption of theſe Churches of having the Spirit of God, or being taught immediatly thereby; for by occaſion thereof, no ſooner doth any one embrace any opinion
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170664:9"/> pretending to Religion, and beginnes to be fortified therein, and that after frequent hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, prayer, faſting, or humiliation, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues to be of the ſame minde, but preſently he thinks himſelfe bound to declare to all the world, what the Spirit of God (as he calles his owne imagination) hath made knowne unto him.</p>
            <p>And hence it is, that at preſent, the World abounds with ſuch variety of opinions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning life and ſalvation, that many a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere heatt, ſeeking for peace and reſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, is kept in perpetuall ſuſpence and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe, whereby their lives become a very burthen to them; and many ſad, and wofull effects, follow thereupon.</p>
            <p>Some by their confidence, and extreamity of zeale, and diligence, get their opinions (how contrary to Scripture ſoever they are) into halfe the people of a Towne, Village and Pariſh; and then there is nothing but <hi>wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, envy, malice,</hi> and <hi>back-biting</hi> one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to the extreme prejudice and unquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the place.</p>
            <p>Some of them crying up their owne experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and the teachings of God within them, affirming that they ſpeak not from Books, or Scriptures, written in Inke and Paper, and in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170664:10"/> Letters and Sillables, but from the inward ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion of the Spirit, induce multitudes to neglect the Scriptures, and to give credit onely to their wilde Notions and Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and though they have no foundation in the plaine expreſſion of the Scripture, or be contrary thereunto, yet are they ſatisfied, that they onely are in the truth, and all other Chriſtians in errour, not examining their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions by the Text, but urging that the Text is to be interpreted by their Opinions and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riences.</p>
            <p>And hence it is, that in the eſteeme of ſome, the Scriptures are of as ſmall value as the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice Book: and to ſpeak of a Chriſt crucified at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> is carnall. Hence it is, that ſome, and thoſe not a few, maintaine there is no ſin, no evill, no difference of things, that all things are good, are one; and that all things are God, and that to ſee or judge any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, is for want of the teaching of the Spirit; and this, though it quite contradict the whole tenour, and plaine open ſcope of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, from the beginning of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> to the end of the <hi>Revelation;</hi> yet paſſeth it for cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and gets ground in all places.</p>
            <p>Hence it is, that ſome men will neither ſtir, nor undertake any thing of any nature, Civill
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170664:10"/> or Naturall, but as they are prompted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, (as they imagine) by the Spirit, or as ſome phraſe it, by the drawings forth of the Father, taken all their inclinations, likings, or diſlikings, to be immediatly from God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by groſſe neglects and failings (to ſay no more) come to be excuſed; and not onely ſo, but expreſly put upon Gods ſcore.</p>
            <p>Hence it is, that ſome after extreame fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and continuance in prayer, (beyond what their bodies could beare,) extent of minde, and intention of apprehenſion, have really beleeved, they have ſeen Chriſt ſtanding by them, and heard him vocally ſpeake unto them, that they have ſeene a light waving a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their beds all the night long; at other times a black darkneſs intermixt: and in theſe extaſies, as they call them, (but indeed fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouriſh diſtempers) they have been bid, as they thought, to doe ſuch things as the holy Scriptures abhorre; and yet could never reſt till they had done them.</p>
            <p>And hence it is, that ſome preſume to be ſo Goded with God, and Chriſted with Chriſt, as they affirme, they are in heaven, and upon the earth; that they are ever well, and that paine is not pain; that all things are nothing, and nothing all things, and glory that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170664:11"/> they are contradictions; Propheſie of things to come, as the day of Judgement; name the time, the very day, ſee it falſe, and yet profeſs it true (in a ſence,) and are beleeved; write bookes of the <hi>Germans</hi> madde mans Divinity, of the occurrences and ſucceſſe of the preſent diſtractions, in ſuch unheatd off expreſſions, concerning King, Parliament, and all Parties, that to a man that gives good heed to the Scriptures, nothing appeares more irreligious; yet through the generall ſuppoſition of the immediate teaching of the Spirit, the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors pleaſe not onely themſeves, but others; and none ſpeaks againſt it, or writes, or prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches againſt it to any purpoſe, leaſt they ſhould break the golden chaine of their own honour or profit; for whoever aſſumes, or maintaines himſelfe to be taught by, or to have the Spirits mediate teaching, is lyable to hold any thing his Fancy preſents to his Imagination, and dares not condemne the falſe aſſumption of Gods holy Spirit, in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, leaſt he ſhould thereby condemne him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; ſince they both have but their owne bare affirmations, for their foundation, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being able to manifeſt, by any thing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, the reall poſſeſſion thereof.</p>
            <p>To this ſad condition are men in theſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170664:11"/> times, brought by this falſ preſence of a Spirit, which once taken up, &amp; inſiſted on, their credit becomes ſo ingag'd, and they are ſo exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delighted, and lifted up, in being thought, the darlings of God, that it is the hardeſt thing in the world, to make them ſee their miſtake; offer but once to bring them into a doubt, or but deſire them to examine how (amidſt ſo many contradictory Opinioniſts, all affirming the Spirit of God for their lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in each) any one of them comes to know himſelfe to be in the right, and they turne the head of one ſide, ſingle, and condemn you as not enlightned, and pray not to trouble them; yet if you enquire, what at any time the Spirit immediatly hath made known unto them, they cannot tell one ſillable, but recite ſome place of Scripture, which by ſerious intention hath imprinted it ſelfe in their minds.</p>
            <p>If you demand a reall Demonſtration of the Spirit, they can give you none, but (peradventure) will tell you, that you muſt awaite Gods time, and he will enlighten you. That their Spirit is as the <hi>white Stone</hi> in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> the name whereof no body knew, but he that received it; making uſe of falſe, darke, and miſterious Scriptures (inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170664:12"/> for another end) to prove that they are unable by any ſound argument, or ſenſible de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration to manifeſt: Whereas, were they really endowed therewith, they could not conceale it, nor we be unconvinced of its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and ſupernaturall Power, but muſt needs bend our knees, and hearts in acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof.</p>
            <p>If we urge the Scriptures againſt them, they tell us the <hi>Letter</hi> killeth, abuſing, and that ſo groſly that place of Scripture, to the uphold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their own vain imagination; nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more evident, then that by <hi>Letter,</hi> in that place of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> is to be underſtood the Law: and by Spirit: the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>And if men did not too much Idolize their owne fancies, it would ſoone appear, That now in our times we have no Preacher of the Goſpel but the Scriptures; which being the infallible Word of God, <hi>the Word of Truth,</hi> Eph. 1. 13. <hi>not the word of man, but (as it is in truth) the Word of God.</hi> 1 Theſ. 2. ver. 13. <hi>which was not yea, and nay, but yea,</hi> 2 Cor. 1. ver. 18, 19. 20. <hi>The Word of God that abideth for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi> Is it not ſtrange, that our pretended Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of all ſorts, ſhould ſo far prevaile upon the minds of men, as to draw them from gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving eare, to what this Word of truth plainly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170664:12"/> and evidently holdeth forth, for the peace of their minds, and direction of their lives; and take up their time and thoughts wholly, or principally, with their uncertain &amp; fallible Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, making them in effect, forſake theſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving fountains, and digg to themſelves broken Ciſterns, that can hold no water.</p>
            <p>Nay, a wonderfull thing it is, that it ſhould be received for a currant truth, That this, the greateſt bleſſing the World knows, this word of the ever living God, ſhould now come to be eſteemed, but as a dead <hi>Letter;</hi> this <hi>ſword of the Spirit,</hi> that forceth it ſelf into our dead naturall underſtandings, plants it ſelf there, makes us one with it: and forms us new; this regenerating word, this immortall ſeed, ſhould be ſo undervalued, as to paſſe but as a dead <hi>Letter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Time was, that it was otherwiſe in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> when our fore-Fathers would have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven any thing in the world; yea, many of them gave up their lives, rather then they would part with the ſmaleſt part of this precious Word, tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> by the firſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere profeſſors of true Chriſtian doctrins; but then Godlineſſe was eſteemed the greateſt gain, and the iniquity of Learning, was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived to ſo much impudence, as to make a gain
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170664:13"/> of Godlyneſſe, to make a trade of Religion, and to become rich by pretended preaching. Nor weaned they the people from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to give eare to their notions, and opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; telling them they had the Spirit, and that the Scriptures were but a dead letter; but invited and perſwaded all men, to a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent conſideration of the true ſcope and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of them.</p>
            <p>Neither did they preferr the underſtanding of men, with difficult points, or obſcure do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrins; but (as <hi>Luther</hi>) inſiſted altogether up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Doctrin of free Juſtification by Chriſt alone; and (in way of thankfulnes for ſo great a benefit) invited all men, to live righteouſly, Godly, and ſoberly in this preſent world; therein following the example of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and the very end, ſcope, and <hi>main deſign of the Scriptures;</hi> which is that <hi>unum neceſſarium,</hi> and which, if people did rightly and ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mind, they would not ſo eaſily be drawn to follow ſuch Teachers, or to give eare to ſuch Sermons; whereby they are alwaies learning, but never come to the knowledge of this one neceſſary truth.</p>
            <p>For, how long work ſoever, Miniſters and pretended Preachers, make of it, to maintaine themſelves, and families in wealth, plenty, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170664:13"/> honour, neceſſary Doctrins are not at all hard to be underſtood, nor require long time to learne them; and if it did not concerne their livelihood, and profeſſion, to make men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, they were people would ſoone under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand ſufficiently for their eſtabliſhment, and comfort, <hi>and would fall to practice,</hi> that ſo they might become an honour to their profeſſion of Chriſtianity; for the Scriptures, or word of God, having once planted this truth in the underſtanding, <hi>viz.</hi> That it is the bloud of Chriſt, which cleanſeth us from all ſinne; this Evangelicall truth of its own nature, would inſtantly ſet man on work to do the will of him, that hath ſo loved him, and conſtrain him to walk in love as Chriſt hath loved: ſo that after this, all the care would be, how to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the Goſpel, by making our light to ſhine forth before men, that others ſeeing our good works, may glorifie our Father which is in Heaven.</p>
            <p>But this is no profitable way, for any of our pretended Preachers, this Doctrin is to ſoone learned; for if men once come, to know that this ſhort leſſon is ſufficient; what will they regard? either printed diſcourſes, or Sermons, and if once they find <hi>them alſo</hi> full of uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170664:14"/> contradiction, and unneceſſary things, they'le not part with their mony for ſuch traſh, when they may go to the two breaſts of Chriſt himſelf, freely at all times, <hi>to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> and buy this ſweet milk and hony, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mony and without price; and if men and women come once to underſtand this, they will not comber themſelves with many things but poſſeſſing this unvalluable truth, will ever worſhip God <hi>in Spirit and in Truth;</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare unto others this bleſſed one neceſſary comfortable way, and that not by preaching or long ſet ſpeeches: which are apt to deceive; but by conferences, and mutuall debates, one with another, (the beſt way for attaining a right underſtanding) far excelling that which is called preaching. But then, how ſhall <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrius</hi> and the Crafts-men live? even by ſome lawfull calling, this being the moſt pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pably deluſive of any in the world, and it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtrange, that all men do not diſcerne and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void it.</p>
            <p>It is ſo, as cunningly as it is carryed, &amp; as high in repute as it is, &amp; hath long time been, having no foundation but in the weake credulity of men; for if men but once conſider it, their Sermons will appear to be but as common diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, full of miſtakes, errors, and at the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170664:14"/> leaſt altogether uncertaine: and that all their preachings and prayings are only for mony, and that their greateſt skill and labour, is to hold men ever in ſuſpence; and upon pretence of truth, to give them a baſtard Scholaſtick knowledge, which only ſerve to make men proud, wrangling <hi>Sophiſters,</hi> and Diſputers, vain boaſters, talkers, buſie-bodies, cenſurers, <hi>Phariſees,</hi> wiſe in their own eyes, and deſpiſing others, void of all true piety or reall Chriſtian vertue: and no marvaile.</p>
            <p>For ſuch as the tree is, ſuch ever will be the fruit; they boaſt to have the Spirit of God, &amp; you ſee it is but boaſting, or their own ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination only: and in the mean time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> take the Scriptures for a dead <hi>Letter;</hi> and either reject them, or make them ſpeak according to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of their own Imaginations; and ſo inſtead of being reall, are at beſt but fantaſtick Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, uncertain (if not falſe) Teachers: and ſuch are their fruits. The greateſt part of their time, wherein they ſhould be imployed to feed the hungry, cloath the naked, or in viſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fatherleſſe &amp; widdow, or in delivering the Captive, and ſetting the oppreſſed free, (all which are workes, ſo fully and plainly ſet forth in Scripture, as moſt pleaſing to God) being ſpent in talking upon ſome hard texts
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170664:15"/> of Scripture, ſuch are their Sermons, or in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes &amp; conteſts, upon ſome nice &amp; difficult queſtions. And this exerciſing themſelvs there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in, week after week, and day after day, and in faſtings and repetitions, and in writing of theſe doubtfull Sermons, is by them called a Religious exerciſe, and thoſe who can but at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to ſo much boldneſſe and utterance, as to ſpeak and pray an howre, two or three, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, take upon them, and are reputed, <hi>guifted Chriſtians,</hi> and principall religious perſons, when as many of them get good eſtates by ſo doing, good benefices, and others who make not a trade of it, as many devout paſtors do; yet gaine ſo much credit thereby, as doth much increaſe their Trades, and advance their Cuſtom and dealing in the world, and now and then helps to a good round Office. And whilſt any of this ſtrain of Chriſtians, may live in this kind of devotion twenty years, preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for twenty or forty ſhillings a year, and have the repute, of a moſt religious knowing Chriſtian, from the teſtimony of the moſt grave, learned, and ſolemn paſtors of all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, if but a part of their religious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burſments be ſpent upon them, it is not to be wondered at, that ſo few are found to ſerve God ſincerely in the way of pure and undefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170664:15"/> Religion, which would plume their Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocks feathers, and coſt them more in one year, then all their lip-ſervice, and Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devotion, doth many of them in their whole life-time.</p>
            <p>Nay, ſo impudent are many of theſe proud boaſting Churches, (who glory to follow preciſely the pattern ſhewed in the mount) that contrary to all example of the Apoſtles and firſt Chriſtians; they can content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be known uſurers, and thoſe that are not ſuch themſelves, can allow it in their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Members, their Paſtors, Elders, and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons can tolerate it, and why not, as well as for their paſtors to take monies from ſuch, as are of leſſe abilitie then themſelves; nay, do not many of them ſpend the greateſt part of their time, either in making, buying, and ſell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of baubles and toyes, ſuch as ſerve only to furniſh out the pride, ſuxury, and fantaſticall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the world; yea, view them well in their apparell, from head to foote; conſider them in their dyet and uſuall feaſtings; in their furniture for their houſes, even in theſe ſad and miſerable times; and then ſay, whether their ſilks, their fine and delicate linnen, their Laces, Beavers, Pluſhes; their Fancies, Plate, Rings, and Jewells; do not demonſtrat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:170664:16"/> from what roote they are, that they are meere worldlings indeed, and Chriſtians only in name and tongue, and not that neither, if they are well obſerved.</p>
            <p>For there are many amongſt them, for ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering and back-biting; for circumvention, and an hipocriticall carriage, ſhall vie and compare with any ſort of men in the world, they can play the part of Spies, Intelligencers, plot and betray, upon pretence of intimacy, of endeared friendſhip and familiarity, eat, drink, be merry with you, day after day, week after week, for months, yea for many years, and after al: profeſſe boldly, openly, confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, before their Church, to Neighbors, friends, or ſtrangers, that all this intimacy, friendſhip, familiarity, was only and meerely to deceive, and to diſcover what might be, to miſchief, the parties with whom they held it: ſhall we aske which of the Apoſtles was a ſlanderer, a ſpy, an Intelligencer, a betrayer; certainly none but <hi>Judas,</hi> and the followers of <hi>Judas;</hi> let them henceforth profeſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, at leaſt, let all that know them, ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count them, unles they manifeſt their ſpeedy true repentance, for bringing ſuch reproach <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the profeſſion of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170664:16"/>
            <p>But what will ſuch men ſtick at, as have once dared to diſſemble before God, to call themſelves Preachers, and are not: to gather Churches, and to joyn and continue in the fellowſhip of meere mock-Churches, that dare attempt the Ordinances with prophane hands, without, and before Commiſſion given from above, that dare pretend Commiſſion, and yet can ſhew no ſeale, no letters of credit from Heaven, that dare affirm their own o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions and Sermons, to be the word of God: and all this after admonition, from ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons too, as out of Conſcience have ſeperated from them, againſt whom alſo they perſiſt to ſhoote their moſt ſharp and poyſoned Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes; even bitter words, falſe invectives, lyes, and ſlanders.</p>
            <p>O therefore conſider this! all ye whoſe Conſciences, are yet ſound amongſt them, or but a little taynted, and ſee into what a wretched condition ye may be led before ye are aware; there is no ſtop in wickedneſſe, but a progreſſe from one degree of evill to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, unleſſe at firſt: therefore ſtop in time, and come out from amongſt them, leaſt ye ſoone partake with them in their ſinnes; and neither approve, nor connive at what you ſee and know to be againſt the judgment of your
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170664:17"/> Conſciences, leaſt in time you become as the worſt and vileſt of them.</p>
            <p>Study the Scriptures, that word of truth: bleſſe God for them, forſake them not for the vain traditions of men, for the uncertain no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Doctrines, and comments of pretended Preachers; and be certain of this, that you may as ſoone as they themſelves, come to a good and right underſtanding therein,—and that you may do ſo. Read them with theſe Conſiderations.</p>
            <p>That although whatſoever is written, is written for our learning, and that we have great cauſe, to be thankfull to God, for vouchſaffing us, the knowledge of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall wayes, of his diſpenſations to man, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſeverall times, and ages, which were from <hi>Adam,</hi> (which was the firſt) unto the time of the deſcending of the holy ſpirit, (which was the laſt:) yet are we ſeriouſly to know, that this laſt diſpenſation of the holy ſpirit, is that which principally concerneth us rightly to underſtand, and to apply to our ſelves, both for our comfort and rule of life; for unto this time and depenſation doth our bleſſed Saviour himſelf referre us, ſaying, <hi>I will ſend you another Comforter,</hi> he ſhall lead you into all truth, he ſhall bring to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170664:17"/> the things that I have told you: and he performed his promiſe effectually to the Apoſtles, whoſe writings we have, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining what the ſame ſpirit taught unto them; the truth whereof, they were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled, and did, confirm with miracles, ſo as it might be as truly ſaid of them, as it was of Chriſt our Lord; that they taught as men having authority, and not as the Scribes, nor as the uncertain phariſaicall teachers of theſe times.</p>
            <p>Unto which word of theirs, we are prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally to give heed: but therein alſo, we are chiefly to diſcover and to mind, what that Doctrine was, which they by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, were ordained to preach? becauſe that being underſtood and believed, doth give the beleever thereof, the name and being of a Chriſtian, how plain and brief ſoever it be; for we muſt note, that there are many things written by the Apoſtles upon occaſions, that concerned only or chiefly, the times wherein they wrote, and the places and perſons to whom they wrote, which is the true cauſe that many things are too hard for us to underſtand; but there was one univerſall Doctrine, which they were to preach to all Nations,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170664:18"/> where with all their writings do abound, and which is very plain and eaſie to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood.</p>
            <p>And this is it, namely, that the ſame Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus whom the Jewes crucified, was Lord and Chriſt: That he is the propitiation for our ſins, and not only for ours, but for the ſins of the whole world, That it is the bloud of Chriſt which cleanſeth us from all ſinne, That his love is ſo exceeding to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, that even when we were ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Chriſt dyed for us: This was the Doctrine which begot people unto the faith, and made them Beleevers: and they uſed no other inducement, unto Beleevers, to walk as becometh this Goſpel (or glad tydings of peace and reconciliation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and us,) but this, ye are bought with a price, therefore honour God, both in your bodies, and in your ſpirits: their ſtrongeſt Argument to perſwade, being this and the like: That the love of God which bringeth ſalvation unto all men, hath appeared, teaching us, to deny all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe &amp; unrighteouſnes of men, and to live righteouſly, godly, and ſoberly in this preſent world: that we ſhould love as Chriſt hath loved, who gave himſelf an Offering
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170664:18"/> and a Sacrifice for us: ſo that if we would try each others Faith, we are to conſider each others love; ſo much faith, ſo much love; ſo much love, ſo much pure and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled Religion; extending it ſelf to the fatherles and to the Widdow; to the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, the naked, ſick, and impriſoned; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evident, that he who hath this worlds goods, and ſuffereth his brother to lack, hath not the love of God in him, yea though he have never ſo great parts of knowledg, zeale, tongues, miracles, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing void of love, he is nothing: plainly manifeſting that all other Religions, are but as defiled and impure in compariſon of this.</p>
            <p>And theſe are the Doctrines, which make good the rejoyning of the Angels, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glory to God in the higheſt, in earth peace, good will towards men: Theſe are ſufficient, and in theſe do all ſorts of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians agree, and never had diſagreed but for falſe Teachers, Wolves in ſheepes Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; who crept in to devoure the flock: cauſing divers ſtrifes and contentions, about genealogies, and about the Law, which made the Apoſtle abundance of trouble, crying out, <hi>O fooliſh Galathians who hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170664:19"/> you;</hi> telling them plainly, if righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe came by the Law, then Chriſt dyed in vain; others, it ſhould ſeem, fell to obſerve Dayes and Times, Sabaoths and Weeks, juſtifying themſelves, and cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring others: provoking the Apoſtle to tell them, he was afraid of them, that he had beſtowed labor in vain upon them, earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſiring them, to let no man deceive them, in reſpect of an holy day, or of the new Moon, or of the Sabaoth, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The truth is, and upon experience it will be foudn a truth: that once exceed theſe plain indiſputable Doctrines, and you will be ever to ſeeke; for though it be a kind of happineſſe, to read in <hi>Geneſis</hi> the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of God towards our firſt Parents, to <hi>Abel, Cayne, Enoch,</hi> to <hi>Noah</hi> and the world that periſhed in the floud; to ſee his migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty power at the Confuſion of <hi>Babell:</hi> his love to <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Sarah,</hi> to <hi>Iſaac, Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> and the twelve Patriarks, to ſee their way of worſhip, to obſerve his mighty wonders in <hi>Egypt,</hi> in the Wilderneſſe, and in the promiſed Land, under the Judges: <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David, Solomon,</hi> and the reſt of the Kings of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael:</hi> To know with what power he ſpake by his holy
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170664:19"/> Prophets in all times, even to <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt.</p>
            <p>Yet when we have done all, we muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that very many things exceed our underſtandings, and that we draw no comfort like unto this, that unto Chriſt, do all theſe beare witneſſe: and though we have great cauſe to bleſſe God, for thoſe wonderfull things we read of the life of Chriſt, of his wiſdom, goodneſſe, and power; by which he beat down the wiſdom craft, and policy of the Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, of the high Prieſt and great ones of the world: and whereby he made it manifeſt, that he was indeed the Chriſt, yet draw we no comfort like unto that, which the Apoſtles publiſh't by the power of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit. the comforter promiſed by Chriſt before his Aſſention: becauſe by this diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of God, only, do we come to know the benefits of Chriſts death, and that he is the end of the Law for righteouſneſſe, and the propitiation for our ſinnes; whereby we have peace of Conſcience, and joy in the Holy-Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>We Read, with thankfulneſſe to God, the Acts of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> all the Epiſtles of <hi>Paul,</hi> of <hi>Peter, James, Jude,</hi> and the Epiſtles
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170664:20"/> of <hi>John,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Revelat.</hi> to St. <hi>John:</hi> But we muſt ſtill acknowledge, that there are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry many things in them all, which wee apprehend not fully. We Read of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>angeliſts, Prophets, Paſtors, and Teachers, and of the ordering and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating of Churches, and of gifts given to all theſe from on high; but not ſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſt, as to leave the Conſcientious without diſpute, and difference thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: nor ſo collected into any one Book, as to convince, that God now under the Goſpel, ſo exactly enjoyned Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, as he did under the Law; where <hi>Moſes</hi> was expreſſely commanded to write particularly all that was required, not lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving out ſo much as Candleſticks, Snuffers, or Beſomes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And when we come to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the Churches, or their Paſtors, and their abilities of our times, with thoſe we read of: or the infallible power by which they ſpake, with the uncertaine Doctrines of ours, alas we muſt lay our hands upon our mouths, and hide our faces, as children uſe to doe, when they are diſcovered by people of underſtanding, at their childiſh immitations, of Chriſtnings and Feaſtings; where, in a low and miſerable weake forme
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170664:20"/> they counterfeit things reall: ſo that if we ſhall deale plainely with our ſelves, we muſt confeſſe, wee are at a loſſe in theſe things, and that hence onely is our rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, <hi>That wee undoubtedly know Jeſus Chriſt and him Crucified, and knowing him, accompt all things as loſſe and dung in Compariſon of him: and that we may be found in him, not having our owne righteouſneſſe which is of the Law, but the righteouſneſſe which is of God in him:</hi> ſo that the whole Scriptures to us, is as the Field mentioned in the Goſpel, and <hi>this the JEWELL,</hi> for which the wiſe Merchant, <hi>ſould all that ever he had to purchaſe it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And truely, if the Traders in Divine things, truely conſider <hi>this,</hi> how learned ſoever they are in Arts and Sciences, in all kinds of Readings and Languages, and how mighty and skilfull ſoever they would be thought in the Expoſition, opening, and interpretation of all places of Scripture, when they come to caſt up their account, poſſibly; nay, certainly, (if they are ſerious therein) they will accompt all as nothing for <hi>this Pearle,</hi> which paſſeth value, they will ſell <hi>All</hi> to purchaſe it; and rejoyce ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170664:21"/> in the exchange, as the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable that ever they made.</p>
            <p>And this certainly would be done fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently by all who with honeſt and good hearts Read the Scriptures; were they not kept from it by faſe Teachers, who hold them in ſuſpence for their own advantage, ever raiſing, and ſtarting new Queſtions, and new Opinions, whereby men are ever learning, but never at reſt in the knowledge <hi>of his one neceſſary truth:</hi> but are toſt too and fro, with every winde of Doctrine: and all by giving eare to thoſe that call themſelves Preachers, but are not: that pretend to expound the Scriptures, when as they raiſe nothing but doubts, and dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them; that ſay they Interpret, when they are to ſeeke for the meaning; being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together doubfull and uncertaine in all they doe.</p>
            <p>And therfore much more happy are they, who read with honeſt and good hearts, and only Read, and conſiderately lay to heart; giving no eare to theſe charmers: theſe doubtfull Eexpoſitors, theſe mocke-Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, with their trumpery Sermons, ſtuft with naught, but uncertainety, and fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke doctrines, which in the day of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170664:21"/> neceſſity of mans Conſcience, prove like a broken Reed, that inſtead of help, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wounds.</p>
            <p>Nor let any man henchforth wonder, whence ſo many ſeverall and ſtrange opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions ſhould ariſe, by which the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes even rent and torne in peeces? It is from this kind of Preachng, and falſe Expoſition of the Holy Scriptures. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, in more ancient times, with the Law and the old Teſtament, as <hi>Petrus Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus, (de Republ. Lib. 2. chap.</hi> 17.) brings to light: affirming, <hi>That howſoever the Law was Read amongſt them in the former times, either in puplicke or in private, yet the bare Text was onely Read, without gloſſe or deſcant,</hi> Interpretatio Magiſtrorum nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, commentatio nulla; <hi>but in the ſecond Temple, when there were</hi> no Prophets, <hi>then did the Scribes and Doctors (mock Prophets, as our mock Preachers) begin to Comment, and make their ſeverall Expoſitions on the holy Text:</hi> Ex quo natae diſputationes &amp; ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae contrariae; <hi>from whence</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſprung up debates, and doubtfull diſputations: and moſt probable it is</hi> (ſaith another upon him) <hi>that from this liberty of Interpretation ſprung
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170664:22"/> up diverſity of judgements, from whence aroſe the ſeverall Sects of Phariſes, Eſſees and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces; who by their difference of Opinions, did diſtract the multitude, and condemne one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Even ſo in theſe times, when as there are no true Apoſtles, Evaugeliſts, Prophets, Paſtors, or Teachers, endowed with pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er from on high, as all true ones are; by which, they are enabled to divide the word of God aright, to ſtop the mouths of gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers, and to ſay, thus ſaith the Lord, thus ſpeakes the Lord, and not I, <hi>And if an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell from Heaven, preach any other doctrine, let him be accurſed.</hi> In the abſence of theſe, are crept in ſwarmes of Locuſts, falſe Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, men of corrupt minds, making <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize</hi> of the bleſſed Word of Truth, and <hi>for that wicked end,</hi> dreſs it up in what ſhape their Art or Rehtorick can deviſe; and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pretence of expoſition, raiſe thouſands of doubts and diſputes, write millions of books, and preach innumerable Sermons; whereby the people are divided, and ſubdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into Factions, Sects and parties; and whereby the end of the Goſpel, which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects only to peace and love, is moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfully
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170664:22"/> made uſe of, as a fire-brand of quarrells and diſſentions.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, the poor innocent Dove, that deſirs to injoy the peace of his mind in this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num neceſſarium,</hi> that little Doctrin <hi>of Chriſt crucified, and to walke in love, ever worſhiping God in Spirit, and in the Truth, diſ-intangled from all formes, as things he finds uncertain, diſ-ingaged from all falſe Churches (and cannot find a true one) that in all things gives thanks, and dares not pray, but for what he needs, nor joyn with any, where he is not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore agreed what to aske,; This innocent dove findes not a place to reſt his foot in, but is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the game of theſe birds of prey, theſe Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, Vultures, and Harpies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O that all ingenious men would lay theſe things to heart! that they would looke more exactly into theſe Churches, more boldly &amp; firmly, trying, examining &amp; weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them in the ballance: that they would ſhake off that vaile of ſuperſtition, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend reſpect to mens perſons; whereby they are over-awed into a high eſteeme of meer vanities, empty ſhels without kernells, empty clouds that hold no water. That they would conſider, how extreamly parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al they are in judging of things; For, who is
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170664:23"/> he, that doth not exceedingly condemn the impudence of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> in offering to buy the holy Spirit of God with mony, purpoſely to have made a gain thereof; and yet can daily ſee men counterfeit the having of the Spirit, and pretend to preach and to pray by it; when as it is evident, they have it not, and yet are no whit troubled at this, though they ſee it done alſo, even for filthy luchre, vain glory, or other vile reſpects, as he intended.</p>
            <p>But all are not a like guilty, many through weakneſſe, and a prepoſterous zeale, being carryed with the ſtream and current of the times; and many there are, who have run themſelves quite out of breath, in ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after peace, and reſt, in the various waies of theſe Churches, and from one Church way to another; but find none to comfort them, nothing to eſtabliſh them; confeſſing, that inſtead of reall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, they find only names; inſtead of power in them, they find only formes, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions, likeneſſes and imitations, meere pictures, and Images without life, altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dead and comfortleſſe; and are held up meerely by the power of Art, craft, and pollicy of men, not without the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170664:23"/> of corrupt authorities, &amp; oppreſſive Stateſ-men; who find it (as it hath ever proved) a notable means to devide the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, making uſe thereof, to their wicked and tyrannous ends; But God in theſe times hath had inſtruments, to lay all kinds of deluſion open: ſo that henceforth, if men continue in theſe evill waies, they are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether inexcuſable.</p>
            <p>Neither will men ever live in peace, and quietnes one with another, ſo long as this vaile of falſe counterfeit preaching, remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth before their eyes, nor untill the mocke Churches are overturned and laid flat; For ſo long as men flatter themſelves in thoſe vaine waies, and puffe themſelves up with vaine thoughts, that they are in a way well pleaſing to God, becauſe they are in a Church way, as they call it, or becauſe they are able to ſpeak long together (which they call preaching) they are for the moſt part regardles of ſtoring their minds with truths reall Chriſtian virtue, little or nothing care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, either for publick Juſtice, Peace, or free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom amongſt men; but ſpend their time in endleſſe diſputes, in condemning and cenſuring thoſe that are contrary mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; whereby nothing but heats and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170664:24"/> are ingendred, backbiting and ſnarling at all that oppoſe them, will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther buy, nor ſell with them, if they can chuſe, nor give them ſo much as a good looke; but on all occaſions are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to Cenſure, one to be carnall, another erronious; one an Atheiſt, another an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick, a Sectary, Sciſmatick, a Blaſphemer, a man not worthy to live, though they have nothing whereof to accuſe him; which in the true Scripture ſence, will beare the title of an offence, but are ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in their ſpirits againſt him, becauſe happily he ſpeaketh againſt their Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and frequently ſheweth the vanity, and emptineſſe of thoſe things wherein they glory, and by which they diſtinguiſh themſelves from other men.</p>
            <p>So that it were much better for the Common-wealth, that all mens mindes were ſet at Liberty, from theſe entangle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that ſo there might be an end of wrangling about ſhaddows; for if men were once free from this Church-bondage, they would by reading the Scriptures with ſuch like conſiderations, as are before ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, ſoone come to be able to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the intent, &amp; ſubſtantiall ſcope there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170664:24"/> and become ſubſtantiall Chriſtians; full fraught with true Chriſtian virtue, and reall godlineſſe, which would incline them to a tenderneſſe of ſpirit towards all thoſe they ſaw in any errour; make them to compaſſionate mens failings, and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities; and be ready to help the diſtreſſed. and any waies afflicted: it would enlarge their hearts toward all men, making them like unto our heavenly Father, who cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his Sun to ſhine on the juſt, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt: that giveth to all men liberally, and upbraideth no man.</p>
            <p>Certainely, were we all buſied onely in thoſe ſhort neceſſary truths, we ſhould ſoon become practicall Chriſtians; and take more pleaſure in <hi>Feeding the hungry, Cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing the naked, viſiting and comforting of the ſicke, releeving the aged, weake and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent;</hi> in delivering of Priſoners, ſupporting of poore families, or in freeing a Common wealth from all Tyrants, oppreſſors, and deceivers, (the authors and promoters of all corruption and ſuperſtion) thereby ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſting our univerſal love to all mankind, without reſpect of perſons, Opinions, Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties, or Churches; doubtleſſe there were no way like unto this, to adorne the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170664:25"/> of Chriſt; men and women ſo exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing themſelves, and perſevering therein, might poſſibly deſerve <hi>the name of Saints;</hi> but for men to aſſume that title for being a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> an <hi>Independent, Browniſt, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſt,</hi> or for being of this or that opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or of this or that forme of Worſhip, or for being able to Pray, and Preach (as they call it) three or foure houres together, ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their own uncertain notions, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures, or for looking more ſadly, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly then other people, or for dreſſing themſelves after a peculiar manner: or for pretending to have the Spirit of God, though they are ever to ſeeke about the meaning of the Scriptures: or for ſucking in, and ſighing out reproaches, and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders againſt their neighbours? proceeds from meer pride and vanity of mind; when as the beſt of theſe put altogether, amount not to ſo much, towards the making of a true Saint, as one mercifull tender heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed compaſſionate act, for Chriſts ſake doth.</p>
            <p>And therefore thoſe who would truly honour God, let them not think, that he will be flattered with words, or be ſerved with lip ſervice, with that which coſteth
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170664:25"/> little or nothing; but let them reſolve that he expecteth to be ſerved with no leſſe then with all our heart, withall our might, and with all our ſtrength, to be honoured both in our bodies, and in our ſpirits, for they are his.</p>
            <p>It is moſt certain, that men are firſt to know and underſtand, before they can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come practicall Chriſtians, and though the Scriptures are very plain aud full, as to neceſſary knowledge, yet the errors of weake and perverſe teachers do ſo abound, that it is a difficult thing to eſcape them, and to fall into a profitable method of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and meditation of the word of God: wherein may the conſiderations aforemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, prove as profitable, as they are conſcionably intended; but doubtleſſe the beſt way to perfect knowledge, is, and will be, by endeavouring after meetings of people to conferre and diſcourſe together (in a diſcreet, quiet, and well ordered way) upon neceſſary points only: the way of preaching or long ſet ſpeeches, being ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to abundance of error, and inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: and therefore it would be happy, that all wel-meaning people would ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſet themſelves to procure frequent
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170664:26"/> and full meetings, for increaſe of knowledg in all ſorts of people, and no longer to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, either on the publique, or congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Sermons, for information of their underſtandings: it being evident, that they ſerve rather to dignifie the Speakers, and to ſway the hearers into what they pleaſe, then to any juſt or neceſſary end.</p>
            <p>And as every one increaſeth in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, let them know, that God hath not vouchſafed his word unto us, to make us talkers, or diſcourſers only; as the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of many knowing people is, who as ſoone as they arive to a good meaſure of underſtanding, and are thereby freed from the burthens and oppreſſions, which error and ſuperſtition had brought into their Conſciences, inſtead of being thankfull to God for the ſame, by dilligence in the wayes of doing good; they become care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, turning the goodneſſe and truth of God manifeſted in his word to Idleneſſe, if not to wantonneſſe, not caring what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth of the miſeries of the times, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens ſufferings; but ever after, live as in a pleaſing dream; theſe who ever they are, are to be looked upon as the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of men, becauſe the moſt ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full:
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170664:26"/> the moſt oppoſite to the end of their being, the vileſt of Creatures, becauſe ſloathfull Chriſtians: the beſt things, being the worſt, if once corrupted.</p>
            <p>And therefore it will be very good, for every one to ſtir up the knowledg of God that is in him, and to keep it alive by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall practice, upon all occaſions: practice in good and juſt and charitable things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that wherein the Conſcience is moſt delighted; ſo that if any propoſe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves any happines here in this life, it is to be found only in doing of good: the more good, the better contented, and the greater the happineſſe, man being in nothing like unto God, but in doing good, nothing is more acceptable to God, nothing is more pleaſant to Conſcience, his vicegerent in us; to do good therefore, and to diſtribute, forget not, for with ſuch ſacrifices God is well pleaſed: whilſt we have time and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertunity, let us do good unto all men.</p>
            <p>Let us all ſtrive to go on before another in love, and let there be no other ſtrife at all amongſt us; we wiſh with all our ſoules that all reproach, deſpites and envy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings amongſt men might for ever ceaſe, and that difference in judgment, may no longer
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170664:27"/> occaſion difference in affection; there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in our apprehenſion no cauſe at all; but that all men going in their ſeverall wayes of ſerving God, whether publique or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, may nevertheleſſe be free to commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate in all civill Offices of love and true friendſhip, and cordially joyne with any, for a publique good; but if notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all that hath been endeavoured, or hath been ſaid: this Generation of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregationall men ſhall continue to puffe, and ſwell through pride of heart, &amp; to lift themſelves up into the Chayre of the ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and as the man in <hi>Peters</hi> Chayre aſſume a power of life and death over all opinions and wayes not owned by them: as if they were infallible judges of all controverſies, making no ſcruple of blaſting mens good names and reputations, or of undoing of whoſe Families thereby: they muſt then expect to be told their own, and be made appear to the world—as they are,—not as they would be eſteemed.</p>
            <p>It being evident by what hath been ſaid, that although they have boaſted themſelvs to be rich, and increaſed with goods, and to have need of nothing; yet, they are as the luke-warm Church of <hi>Laodicea, miſerable, &amp;
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170664:27"/> wretched, and poore, and blind, and naked</hi>—and for all their bigg and ſwelling con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts of parts, of gifts, of Saint-ſhip, of the Spirit, &amp; (in effect) phariſaically crying out, <hi>Lord we thank thee, we are not as other men,</hi> nor as thoſe poore <hi>Publicans,</hi> that receive all their knowledge of Divine things from the Scriptures onely, and are taught onely thereby; Notwithſtanding theſe bigg ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling words, their Peacocks feathers, being thus pluckt off, you ſee: and they, will they, nill they, muſt alſo ſee, that they muſt be content at laſt, to ſhake hands even with thoſe poore <hi>Publicans;</hi> and acknowledge that they have no other infallible Teacher of Divine things, but the Scriptures; and that they partake no more of the Spirit, then what that bleſſed Word of the Spirit planteth in them.</p>
            <p>And if their conſciences are awakened, will be enforced to forſake their falling Churches: unleſſe for politique ends, they ſhall ſtifle the power of theſe Truths with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them; chuſing rather to periſh in the rubbiſh, then to ſeem to have bin ſo excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly miſtaen; which will prove an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable error; For, however the beſt of men may erre, yet they are the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170664:28"/> worſt of men, that perſiſt in error, after the diſcovery.</p>
            <p>And therefore, if there be any whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences ſhall be fully informed of the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of theſe Churches; and yet for any ends ſhall continue to ſupport the reputation of them; let all ſuch know, that thoſe who dare be ſo impious, as to ſtop the continuall cry of their conſciences, muſt neceſſarily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire in their hearts there were no God, whoſe Uicegerent, Conſcience is; which is the moſt ſad, and dangerous conditon that man can fall into in this life.</p>
            <p>And certainly they will find it far better to forſake their tottering immaginary ſtructures: confeſs their emptines, &amp; ſinfull imitation, taking ſhame unto themſelves<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and giving glory unto God, whoſe name and power they have much diminiſhed, hy affirming thoſe to be Churches which are not, thoſe Paſtors and Preachers which are not, thoſe Saints which are not: his bleſſed Word to be but a dead <hi>Letter:</hi> that to be his Word, which is but conjecturall Sermons; and in cenſuring thoſe to be erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious and carnall Chriſtians, who have more warrant for what they do then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; And then by a more conſiderate,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170664:28"/> ingenious, and Chriſtian-like carriage, to make amends for the future, which would very much rejoyce the herrts of all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that love the Lord Jeſus in ſincerity, whoſe Truth and Glory will be advanced by the Scriptures; when all the roving, wild and wandring immaginations of mens ſpirits, ſhall vaniſh, and come to nought.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Feb.</hi> 23. 1648-49</date>,</dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Imprimatur</hi> THEODORE JENNINGS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
